Welcome to this talk on
thoracic outlet syndrome.
Please take a moment
to pause the video
and review these
session objectives.
Then after you have
watched the complete
video, return to these
objectives and make sure
that you can confidently
accomplish them.
Please do the required
reading before viewing this
lecture and make note of the
two footnotes listed here.
Thoracic outlet syndrome
is actually a group of
diverse conditions with
variable symptomatology
that results from compression
of the neurovascular
bundle. As you can
guess from the title,
this compression occurs at
the thoracic outlet region.
What makes it special
or unique perhaps is
that although it is
a relatively uncommon
condition, the symptoms
can be quite significant.
And these symptoms,
such as pain, numbness,
or weakness, overlap
with more common
conditions, making it
a diagnostic challenge.
So to be able to properly
diagnose it, especially
given that again it is an
uncommon and uncommon condition,
one has to be in a sense
on top of our game in
terms of having sufficient
anatomical knowledge and
reasoning and the ability
to perform a physical
examination to adequately
begin the assessment process.
Thankfully we have other
methods to help us to
determine if indeed a patient
has this condition or not.
Here's a reminder of the
superior thoracic aperture
also referred to as the
thoracic inlet. Clinically
it's referred to as the
thoracic outlet region.
Keep in mind that even
though you see the
bony architecture here
it's more than about
just the bones as we
will go into shortly.
Symptoms of thoracic
outlet syndrome include the
following and for convenience
I have decided to start
them all with the letter
P but hopefully this
will help you to conceptualize
the overall pattern.
One is pain in a shoulder
and or upper extremity
meaning arm forearm and hand.
There may be paresthesia.
These are sensations of
numbness, tingling, or burning.
There can be coldness.
This is both a symptom
that the patient experiences
or a physical sign
that you determine when
you evaluate the patient.
There can be pallor,
meaning paleness of the
extremity, typically from
impaired circulation.
Also, there can be movements
that provoke the symptoms.
This is not universal and
we'll get into this later
with the various types of
thoracic outlet syndrome.
But if it is provoked by
movement, usually it is
overhead movement,
meaning movement of the
extremity above the level
of the shoulder. There
can be poor function.
This can be due to actual
weakness of the upper
extremity. The patient may
note a sensation of
heaviness in the extremity.
There can be a sense
of fatigue or lack of
endurance, meaning that
when they begin using the
arm, for example, it
becomes tired easily or
reproduces the symptoms
such as pain or paresthesia.
It can be atrophy if it
is severe and depending
on the cause and how
long it has been.
It can also affect a
particular side, although
sometimes the symptoms
can be bilateral.
The three types of
thoracic outlet syndrome in
terms of anatomical
etiologies are listed here.
I will review these in
the following slides.
Let's start off with the
first one, neurogenic. In
this instance, there's
compression of the brachial
plexus, which involves the
C5 to T1 nerve roots, and
most often, it involves the
lower plexus, C8 and T1,
therefore the ulnar distribution
of the upper extremity.
There may be severe
weakness in muscle atrophy
if the compression is severe
and or chronic enough.
After neurogenic,
the second most
common, which is a
misnomer because
it's not common,
but in terms of ranking,
it would rank as number
two, would be venous
thoracic outlet syndrome.
This is caused by
compression of the
subclavian vein
or axillary vein,
depending on the site
of the compression.
Lastly, we have
arterial thoracic outlet
syndrome, which is
rare. It is caused by
compression of the
subclavian artery or axillary
artery depending on the
site of compression.
So what is the most
common type of thoracic
outlet syndrome and its
percentage of cases?
Earlier I said that you
do not need to know the
percentages, but I do
want you to know this one.
And here's the
answer. It's mostly
neurogenic, accounting
for over 90% of cases.
The etiology of thoracic
outlet syndrome is often
spoken of as neurovascular
compression, implying that
it involves both neurogenic
and vascular etiologies,
and perhaps there may be
components of both. But
according to the literature,
it's mostly neurogenic.
Clinically, there may be
features of both neurogenic
and vascular types, and
perhaps both are involved.
It may be hard to tell,
especially early on.
or if the clinician is
not fully familiar with
the condition or ways to
go about evaluating it.
Physicians improve by
learning and practicing, and
generally speaking, the more
common a condition is that
one encounters, the more
likely one will be able to
recognize it and better manage
it. In a case of thoracic
outlet syndrome, the cases
will be few and far between.
Even the most common
type, which is
neurogenic, their total
incidence is two to
three cases per 100
,000 people per year.
The venous type is half
to one case per 100
,000 people per year,
and the least common,
arterial thoracic outlet
syndrome, is sporadic.
The typical onset of
thoracic outlet syndrome
is in those between
20 to 50 years old,
and it is more common
in females than males.
Thoracic outlet syndrome may
be classified as congenital,
meaning there is some form
of anatomical defect that
is causing the compression
or puts the patient at
increased risk of the
compression this can be bony in
nature perhaps or from
abnormal myofascial tissue or
vascular tissue there can also
be acquired causes of thoracic
outlet syndrome such as
from trauma these include
sports or repetitive type
activity so it may not always
be recognized as trauma
perhaps it's from surgery or
adaptation to surgery
functional captures the rest and
includes what a patient
does, such as their hobbies,
their stress level, and
basically how they use their
body in their daily lives.
And that can
potentially contribute
to thoracic outlet syndrome.
So what should we look for
in the history? Well, one
is to think of the various
types of symptoms that the
patient has and their
location, including whether it
affects one side or both
sides, or if it's both sides,
whether one side is more
significant than the other.
And because thoracic
outlet syndrome is a
challenging diagnosis,
a lot of the time
you are considering
alternative diagnoses
and figuring out whether
they are a better
explanation for the
patient's symptoms.
We should ask about
provoking factors
such as whether
movement causes the
symptom, the timing
of the symptoms.
An obvious one would be, again,
if the activity causes
symptoms, or whether it's
related in any way to
something new that a patient
did, either recently
or relatively recently.
And one way to assess the
impact of the symptoms on a
patient and judge its severity
is what has the patient
done since the onset of
symptoms in terms of stopping
or modifying anything that
they typically do in their
lives. And of course, we
should inquire about trauma.
What else should
we look for or be
mindful of? One is
the smoking status of
the patient. Another
is advanced age.
With advanced age, unfortunately,
we need to consider
other diagnoses and
typically more serious
diagnoses, or at least a
patient might be more seriously
affected by whatever
condition that they have.
We need to be mindful of
severe symptoms or if a
patient's symptoms are
worsening, especially if they
are worsening at a rapid
pace. If a patient has
non-musculoskeletal symptoms,
we need to be mindful
of that, such as, for
example, chest pain. It
doesn't mean that it can't
end up being musculoskeletal,
but we should at least
be mindful of symptoms
that might suggest another
organ or body system.
and we need to
understand and look for
constitutional symptoms
and red flags in general.
So symptoms or signs
of weight loss,
night sweats,
having shortness of breath,
having hemoplysis, and
so forth would alert
us to the possibility
that something serious
might be going on,
even if the patient
does end up having
thoracic outlet syndrome.
One only needs to look
at the various terms that
are used to describe
thoracic outlet syndrome.
This is because
there are various
potential causes,
anatomically speaking, for
the syndrome in a
particular patient.
And therefore, it's
important to understand the
anatomy and the relationship
between structures and we
will go into this shortly
for some of these terms
that are listed there might
be slight variations so
for example costal
clavicular space syndrome may
simply be referred to as
costal clavicular syndrome
if we look at the bottom at
the bottom term the Paget
von Schroeder syndrome which
is also known as venous
thoracic outlet syndrome or
another term is primary effort
thrombosis we can appreciate
the fact that at times
there are there's a more
serious underlying cause so
in terms in the case of
a blood clot it can cause
significant symptoms and in
the worst case scenario be life
-threatening so let's
dive into the anatomical
considerations and thoracic
valve syndrome there are three
primary regions of entrapment
that one needs to keep in
mind the first is the
interscaling triangle as you can
guess from the name it is
this this is a space through
which important structures
pass formed by scaling
muscles in this case it's the
anterior and middle scaling
muscles in the neck through
the space the brachial
plexus as well as the subclavian
artery passed through.
This is the most common
site for brachial plexus
impingement, meaning
pressure or irritation.
The second space is the
costoclavicular space.
Think back to the last
slide with the term
costoclavicular space
syndrome, which indicates
that the structures
of either the brachial
plexus subclavian artery
or subclavian vein
may be impinged or may be
irritated in the space as
they travel through the
space leading to symptoms but
of these three structures
that pass through this
costoclavicular space the most
commonly compressed at the
site is the subclavian vein
finally we have the subcorchord
space also known as the
retro pectoralis space
or subcoracoid pectoralis
minor space. And here, the
brachial plexus axillary
artery and axillary vein pass
through. These two lattice
structures are a continuation
of the subclavian artery
and vein as it makes its
way through the axilla and
into the upper extremity.
In this subcoracoid
space, we can
get neurovascular
bundle compression.
And this can occur
almost as commonly
as impingement in
the interscaling
triangle, as already
described above.
Here we have a
diagram that nicely
summarizes these three spaces.
Starting most superiorly, we
have the scaling triangle,
also known as the
interscaling triangle, that's
formed anteriorly by the
anterior scaling muscle and
the posterior border of
this triangle is formed by
the middle scaling muscle
and then the base of the
triangle which is not well
shown here is the first rib
so through this triangle we
have trunks of the brachial
plexus as well as the
subclavian artery and sub
as well as the subclavian
artery that passes through
the subclavian vein is
anterior and medial to the
interscalion triangle so it
is not passing through the
triangle and therefore it
is not a site of impingement
and based on this picture
we can appreciate how if
there is an abnormality of
the first rib or if there
is something called a
cervical rib meaning a rib
that forms in the cervical
spine how if this impinges
on the brachial plexus or
subclavian artery that this
can lead to symptoms of
thoracic outlet syndrome
next we have the costoclavicular
space which is formed
by the clavicle between
the clavicle superiorly and
the first rib inferiorly
and here we again have the
brachial plexus as well as
the subclavian artery and
in this case the
subclavian vein that passes
through and in fact in
this costal cavicular space
if again if there's
abnormalities of the first rib
one can imagine if there
is a sufficiently superior
or elevated first rib
how that would narrow
the space and can impinge
upon these structures.
And the most commonly
affected structure in
terms of thoracic
outlet syndrome in this
costoclavicular space
is the subclavian vein.
And lastly, we have the
pectoralis minor space. And
technically, this is not
part of the thoracic outlet,
but it is a common cause,
is almost as common of
a site as the interscaling
triangle for compressing
the neurovascular
bundle and we can
imagine how conditions
such as pectoralis
minor hypertrophy or
hypotonicity or if there's
some abnormality of the
ribs such as somatic
dysfunction how this
can narrow the space
and lead to impingement
of structures in this
pec minor space or
pectoralis minor space.
Here we have an illustration
of a cervical rib and
how that if it is sufficiently
large and close to the
brachial plexus in this
example that it can impinge
on that structure and
cause symptoms. On the left
hand side you see the symptoms
and signs for neurogenic
type thoracic Outlet
Syndrome, which again is the
most common. It's most
often from compression of
the brachial plexus in the
anterior scaling triangle.
You also should note the
distribution of symptoms.
Note the significant
percentage involves the upper
extremity. You don't need to
know the exact percentages,
but you should get a rough
idea of the distribution.
If the compression
is severe as well as
prolonged enough, it
can cause symptoms to
include nerve damage
and resulting in loss
of sensation and muscle
atrophy, weakness,
and eventually loss of
function. On the right
-hand side, you see
some common triggers.
Venous thoracic outlet
syndrome, also known as
Pagifon-Schroeder syndrome
or effort thrombosis, is
relatively uncommon compared
to neurogenic thoracic
outlet syndrome. It only
comprises about 10 to 15
percent of cases and is
often from compression of the
subclavian vein within
the costoclavicular space.
The symptoms noted
here overall would be
consistent with a
vascular type phenomenon.
The forearm may be fatigued
within minutes of using it.
There may be variable degrees
of upper extremity swelling,
as well as cyanosis or
subjective heaviness. There
can be paresthesias and
or pain of the upper
extremity, and swelling
may occur in the shoulder,
supraclavicular, or chest
regions, and there can be a
pattern of veins if there is
venous stenosis or occlusion.
This is due to collateral
flow as a compensation.
Clinically, one should
consider thrombosis in
cases of venous thoracic
outlet syndrome depending
on the specifics of
the patient's symptoms.
Again, in terms of
triggers, there can be
repetitive activity,
especially if it is vigorous
or overhead, hence the
term effort thrombosis
as another name that
can be used to refer
to it. Heavy lifting
can also be a trigger.
we can think of it also
in terms of whether
it occurs spontaneously
versus if there's some
trauma to the vein,
such as from a catheter.
And one should also consider
extrinsic compression,
such as from a tumor
pressing on the vein.
Lastly, we have arterial
thoracic outlet syndrome,
which is rare. It only
comprises 2% to 5% of total
cases, and often is from
compression of the subclavian
artery within the scalene
triangle. The symptoms and
signs are noted here because
it is a vascular etiology.
It is also important to
keep in mind important
conditions such as an aneurysm
or thrombus formation,
depending on the specifics
of a patient's symptoms.
For example, if a patient
presents with unexplained
severe pain, loss of
color in the limb,
if there's cold coldness,
and if one does not
detect a pulse or a
very weak pulse, then
consideration should be
given to limb ischemia,
either from a thrombus
formation or an aneurysm.
Arterial thoracic outlet
syndrome is almost always
associated with a cervical
rib or an anomalous
rib, meaning an abnormal
rib. It is typically not
work or trauma related,
but vigorous activity may
be a factor in some
populations, such as athletes.
Based then on these
historical and anatomical
considerations of thoracic
outlet syndrome, what should
the immediate focus of your
clinical evaluation be?
I propose then
that you begin to
consider and identify
potentially serious
or even limb
-threatening conditions.
And you do this by considering
the historical components,
looking for red flags,
and on your examination
evaluating both the neurological
status of the patient
as well as the vascular
status due to the
neurovascular compressive nature
of thoracic outlet syndrome.
Here's a quick list of
some common regions that
you should consider evaluating
for potential either
contribution meaning they're
part of the picture or
perhaps they are the answer
and thoracic outlet syndrome
though in your differential
is not really the
underlying cause but it
makes sense to check the neck
shoulder upper extremity
upper thoracic region and
of course also consider
potentially visceral causes.
You have learned about
visceral somatic reflexes, so
it's important to think of
some important organ systems
that may refer symptoms to
the neck, shoulders, chest,
upper back, or even upper
extremity to consider those
as possibly a mimic, meaning
it causes symptoms of
thoracic outlet syndrome, but
it is really from an organ
cause, or it may actually
contribute to a patient
developing thoracic outlet
syndrome for example if the there
is a pulmonary mass that
results in compression of
the subclavian vessels this
may actually lead to thoracic
outlet syndrome so it is
important to think of it in
that sense also even reproductive
for example if someone
has a ruptured ovarian
cyst that causes enough
bleeding that that extravasates
extravasates to the subphrenic
region, it can actually
even cause shoulder pain.
The most commonly used
clinical test to assess
for thoracic outlet syndrome
is the AdSense test.
According to the first
source listed here, it is
used to determine the state
of the subclavian artery,
which may be compressed
by an extra cervical rib
or by tighten anterior and
middle scalene muscles.
According to the second
source listed here
is used for brachial
plexus impingement
between the anterior
and middle scalene.
So in both instances
we're talking about
assessing for impingement
of a structure, either
the subclavian artery
or the brachial plexus.
This is a picture showing
how to position the
patient's upper extremity
for the AdSense test.
Note how the clinician
stabilizes the patient's
shoulder and monitors
at the radial pulse.
This is tested on
a side of symptoms.
It is important to also
check the radial pulse
before bringing the
patient into this position.
A positive test is where the
radial pulse significantly
decreases or is absent
during this maneuver or if
the test exacerbates the
patient's pain or paresthesia.
In addition to the Adson
tests, there are additional
physical exam tests that
you can perform on a patient
if you clinically want to
determine if there might
be thoracic outlet syndrome.
For example, if the Adson
test is negative but you
still clinically suspect
the condition, or the patient
cannot tolerate the test
for whatever reasons, such
as joint restriction or
pain, then it is useful to
be aware of these tests.
For the purpose of this
lecture, you do not need
to know the specifics
of how to perform these
additional tests, but
do know that they exist.
And by using a combination
of tests, one can improve
the sensitivity and
specificity of making a correct
diagnosis of thoracic outlet
syndrome in a patient.
For the AdSense test
or any physical or
laboratory diagnostic
procedure or imaging
procedure as examples,
one has to keep in
mind the possibilities
of having a false
positive finding and a
false negative finding.
Remedies to combat this
include taking a good
history and performing a
good physical examination.
For thoracic outlet
syndrome, in particular,
given the structural
basis of this condition,
adding the osteopathic
structural examination
is particularly
useful, and it would
be good to make sure
you incorporate that.
Also performing a
combination of tests is
useful because thoracic
outlet syndrome is
relatively uncommon but
yet the symptoms that
are present such as
pain, numbness, tingling,
heaviness, easy
fatigue of the limb,
and other symptoms
and signs, they can
be caused by other conditions
that are more common.
So having other tests to
evaluate for these possibilities
is important. For
example, performing the
Sperling test to look for any
evidence of cervical nerve
root impingement is
useful. Also, checking the
Tenelle sign, also known as
the Hoffman-Tenelle sign,
at the owner groove of
the elbow to look for
owner nerve impingement or
checking the median nerve
at the wrist to look for
any evidence of carpal
tunnel syndrome. These
would be useful and
easy to perform tests
that can help us determine
if a patient indeed has
thoracic outlet syndrome
or perhaps a more common
condition, or perhaps
they have both.
A broad range of
diagnostic methods
exist for diagnosing
or working up
thoracic outlet syndrome.
One can diagnose
it just clinically
with your physical examination
and your history,
and if that is not
clear or one needs
additional support for
diagnosing thoracic
outlet syndrome,
then one can go
to these methods.
And these methods include
radiographs of the spine,
chest, shoulder, and upper
extremity. So for example,
plane films of the
cervical spine may show a
cervical rib. And in that
case, then it would lend
support for that as a cause
of a patient's symptoms.
Magnetic resonance imaging
can be done, something
called MRN, magnetic resonance
neurography can be performed,
for example, to look at
the brachial plexus. A
CT scan can be performed
to look at bony structures.
It gives a more detailed
look than just plain films.
An ultrasound can be performed.
Imaging, excuse me,
functional studies
such as electrophysiologic
studies with EMG
and nerve conduction
study can be done.
Arteriography and angiography
can be performed to
give a better view of the
or to give a view of the
blood vessels to see if
for example their caliber
is is abnormal a more
functional type testing for
circulation would be
hemodynamic testing as well
as using local anesthetic
injections into suspected
structures that can cause
thoracic outlet syndrome,
such as the anterior
scalene. So for example,
in those suspected to,
where the scalene, anterior
scalene is suspected to be
the source of impingement,
if a patient responds
positively to an injection,
then if they ultimately
still need surgery
because the condition was
just partially improved
or comes back or worsens,
then those who initially
had a positive response
to the injection,
94% of them have a positive
outcome after surgery,
versus only 50% of
patients respond
positively to surgery
if initially they
had no response to
the local injection.
So this gives one the sense
of that, well, it should
give one an understanding
that injections, therefore,
can be used not just
to help treat symptoms,
but if you are considering
a particular structure
and the patient responds
even temporarily, then it
lends support to that
structure as being a cause. So
injections can be both
therapeutic and diagnostic.
Here are some important
considerations when it comes
to assessing for thoracic
outlet syndrome. The idea
is that thoracic outlet
syndrome is a relatively
uncommon condition.
So one should look for
conditions that are not
just more common, but can
explain a patient's
symptoms adequately. If
they do, then they have
this alternative diagnosis
and do not have thoracic
outlet syndrome.
But if one determines that
another clinical entity
is present and it explains
the patient's symptoms
to some degree but not
adequately, then there's the
possibility that the
patient may have both this
competing diagnosis as
well as the potential for
having thoracic outlet
syndrome as another diagnosis.
So, again, a patient
can have more than one
diagnosis, and it's
important to weigh what
better explains the
patient's condition.
There's a condition called
double crush syndrome,
for example, where a
patient has thoracic
outlet syndrome and
carpal tunnel syndrome.
syndrome, and this
combination, while in
principle can be present,
is relatively uncommon.
So again, ultimately one
has to make a clinical
determination on what
best explains a patient's
condition and by doing
so we can then address
it and improve their
symptom and function.
So let's revisit the three
primary regions of entrapment
and thoracic outlet
syndrome. It is useful to
know these in order to
accomplish our osteopathic
approach of examining for
relevant anatomy in order to
see if it may be involved
in a patient's symptoms.
At the interscalene triangle,
we have the anterior
scalene muscle that forms
the anterior border,
the middle scalene
muscle that forms the
posterior border of the
triangle, and the first rib
which forms the inferior
border of the triangle.
Next we have the costoclavicular
space and we have
the subclavius muscle
which is or forms the
anterior border of the
space, the clavicle which
forms the superior border
of the space, the anterior
scalene muscle which
forms in this instance
the posterior border of
the space and the first rib
which forms the inferior
border of this space.
So there is some
overlap in terms of the
structures such as the
first rib and the anterior
scaling in terms of
what space involves.
So even though earlier I
had said that typically
it is one of the primary
sites that's thought to
be the cause of entrapment.
The reality is because
of this overlap of
anatomy, perhaps it may not
be so clear all the time.
So in terms of osteopathic
assessment, we can
look, in this instance,
we can look for
clavicular somatic
dysfunction, cervical
somatic dysfunction,
scalene somatic dysfunction,
and first rib
somatic dysfunction.
Last we have the
subcoracoid space.
The coracoid process forms
the superior border, the
pectoralis minor muscle
forms its anterior border,
and the upper rib cage
forms the posterior border.
So looking for somatic
dysfunction in these
regions makes sense, especially
if we are entertaining
the possibility of
compression in this region.
And keep in mind that
the core cord process is
part of the scapula. So
a patient's posture, the
position of their
scapula, and therefore the
ribcage and the upper
thoracic spine, for example,
all of that then plays a
role in the positioning of
the scapula. So even though
just these structures
are listed here because
they technically form the
subcore chord space, from
an osteopathic point of
view, there are other structures
that we can and should
look at when it comes to
osteopathic assessment.
Based on your
readings as well as on
the lecture so far,
please take a few
minutes to complete
this self-assessment.
Here are the answers.
I've titled this slide,
Other Important Structures to
Consider, but I really
want to clearly state that
other does not imply less
important. In fact, any of
these structures are just
as important to consider in
thoracic outlet syndrome,
both to make sure that there
isn't some other factor
that makes you'd think it's
thoracic outlet syndrome
when it is not, as well as
the fact that sometimes
things are not that clear
clinically, or even if it is,
conditions may not respond
to treatment as readily.
So the more of the anatomy
you understand and evaluate
and treat, hopefully the
quicker the patient's
symptoms improve or resolve.
So these considerations
include posture we talked about
the scalings keep in mind
where the scalings originate
from in terms of the
cervical spine and it becomes
apparent that we need to
look at the cervical spine
not just the muscle but for
the somatic this funk other
somatic dysfunctions of
the cervical spine such as
rotations then in the case
of the costoclavicular space
and the structures that
pass through that then we've
talked about first ribs
let's talk about and consider
the clavicle and the vastic
spine is important such
as its role in affecting
potentially sympathetic tone
to the upper extremities
and therefore its impact on
things such as pain sensation
as well as arterial flow,
but also the impact on
the rib cage because ribs
are attached to the thoracic
spine in the back. So one
can argue, too, to evaluate
the sternum in the front.
And here we have upper
extremity. I put in clavicle
again because we can
think of the clavicle in
terms of the upper extremity
so it's important to
consider so things such as
the SC joint the AC joint
and if you study
osteopathic medicine further
we can make additional
diagnoses for the clavicle
itself such as strains
strain patterns in the bone
itself that you can
palpate and treat and make
it less less stiff for
example and more compliant.
So evaluating for
somatic dysfunction
in the shoulder, the scapula,
the upper extremities,
such as at the elbow,
wrists, and hands. And pay
attention to not just bony
findings, but also just
a quick reminder to
consider soft tissue
findings too, which you can
discern by observation and
palpation, for example.
In osteopathy, we often talk
about the interrelationship
between form and function
and one common example
an important example of
this is that of posture in
this picture we see anterior
positioning of the head
neck shoulder and upper
back this is also sometimes
referred to as upper cross
syndrome you do not need to
know the details of what
is listed on this slide but
visually we can appreciate
how this anterior superior
positioning of the upper
back, head, and neck region
adds to mechanical strain
of these regions, both to
the joints as well as to
the myofascial structures.
And because of the
nature of thoracic outlet
syndrome being a compressive
type phenomenon or
compressive entity in the
region of the superior thoracic
inlet, we can appreciate
how even if this
forward posture is not
directly responsible for the
thoracic outlet syndrome
condition that it can
play a role and add to
the patient's symptoms and
at the very least likely
not help the situation.
There are a variety of
modalities available
to address thoracic
outlet syndrome. As
with any condition,
it starts with the
diagnosis and in
thoracic outlet syndrome,
the specific site
of the compression
or knowing that can
be quite useful.
Also, its severity,
patient-specific factors,
such as what can the
patient tolerate, and then
matching the patient's
needs to available options,
and not just their
potential benefit, but also
the risks. So in a
patient that does not have
any significant neurological
or vascular compromise.
So if they don't have
any significant weakness
or signs of muscle
atrophy, then it makes
sense to begin with
conservative management. And
typically that means
physical rehabilitation.
And being future DOs,
of course, we would
want to also include OMT
as a physical option.
And that makes a lot of
sense given the physical
nature of the obstruction
and thoracic outlet syndrome.
And it would be, of course,
important to address
other factors that had
either caused or exacerbated
the patient's symptoms
and making them feel more
comfortable with pharmacological
treatments or injections
can also be useful and
can potentially reduce
impingement. If conservative
management does not
improve the symptoms or the
patient worsens, then it
makes sense to transition
to surgical consideration.
but the key is patient
education monitoring and
an adequate trial of four
to six months as long
as the patient is showing
progress is reasonable.
When patients have failed
conservative management
then surgery becomes an
option to consider and
arterial or venous thoracic
outlet syndrome often
is managed surgically.
Again, depending on the
particular case, there may
be an exception to this.
Neurogenic thoracic
outlet syndrome can be
potentially resolved
with resection of rib
1, and this is often
performed with something
known as scalenectomy
or scalenotomy.
The pros, meaning advantages,
of a surgical approach is
that one can achieve excellent
results in about 95% of
cases in neurogenic thoracic
outlet syndrome, and also
has been shown that there's
greater than a 95% patency
rate in venous thoracic
outlet syndrome five years
after surgical correction.
The disadvantages of surgery
are that complications
can occur, such as
brachial plexus injury.
Being able to
recognize pain referral
patterns is important.
So anyone going into
musculoskeletal medicine,
be it orthopedics,
physical medicine, or
primary care, and of course
OMM should understand
trigger points. In trigger
points there is a tight
muscle focus or foci
meaning multiple spots
in a muscle region
typically that refers pain
or symptoms elsewhere.
Therefore it makes it a little
challenging and confusing
to diagnose if one is not
familiar with it. There
are manuals that one can
look up. For example, the
scaling muscles have trigger
points that can refer
symptoms as shown here to
the upper extremity, to the
chest, and upper back area.
So being able to palpate these
with precision and identify
them and therefore treat
them can allow one to
distinguish whether a patient's
symptoms are due to trigger
points such as in the
scaling muscles versus from
thoracic outlet syndrome.
Techniques that can be
used for thoracic outlet
syndrome include
myofascial release, either
direct or indirect,
soft tissue technique,
balanced ligamentous tension,
which addresses the ligaments,
counter strain,
and even HVLA.
In all cases, think
through the indications and
contraindications for a
particular patient and choose
techniques that are
appropriate for the patient,
that are well tolerated,
and with experience, you
can also modify techniques
to suit the patient.
Ultimately, you will
reassess the patient, not
just their somatic
dysfunction, but also long
-term, their progress,
whether their symptoms
decrease, whether their
function improves, in order
to decide on how to
continue your management.
Here we have a basic contact
to address the cervical
region. The findings may
include cervical segmental
somatic dysfunction such as
an isolated segment or it
could be more general like
cervical muscle hypertonicity
involving the paraspinal
muscles or the scalenes.
Your exact hand contact
can change a little
bit as well as your
forces, but ultimately
you are looking for
an improvement in
whatever somatic dysfunction
you are treating.
The thoracic inlet release
may also be used and
can potentially decrease
myofascial tension and
even skeletal tension
in this upper thoracic
region to help improve
lymphatic flow and potentially
alleviate at least
temporarily mild instances
of impingement of
neurovascular structures.
The exact effect will
depend on the nature of
the patient's condition
as well as the skill of
the provider as well as
the provider's focus.
Using the same basic hand
contact one can address
more of the myofascial
structures and superficial
structures or one can go
more deeply and address the
bony structures such as
the sternoclavicular region
and the first rib regions
so one can again think
of the name and associated
with treating thoracic
outlet syndrome but it is
more important to think of
the anatomy when we are
actually treating it in
order to decide how best to
implement this technique.
RIV1 inhalation somatic
dysfunction can exert a
compressive effect at the
thoracic outlet and result in
thoracic outlet syndrome
symptoms. Therefore, it is
important and relatively easy
to check for this somatic
dysfunction and treat it
with OMT if appropriate.
Here we have the
pectoralis minor. Recall
that this forms the
subcoracoid space. It's
one of the structures
that forms the
subcoracoid space and
it is a common area for
entrapment in Jurassic
outlet syndrome. So it's
important to find the landmark
the coracoid process be
able to go inferior and
medial to that structure
and palpate for a potential
counter-strain point and
we have a simple technique
shown here for counter
-strain of the pectoralis
minor if we understand anatomy
we have options let's
take the example of again
the pectoralis minor and
in this instance we'll use
the example of right ribs
3 4 and 5 being exhaled
so as you have learned this
exhalation dysfunction can
be addressed using muscle
energy for the pec minor
and this is shown in the
picture on the right we can
appreciate how an exhalation
group stretches the pec minor
muscle which has its origin
at the corocord process
we can see how there is an
anatomical and functional
link between these three
ribs and the shoulder and
if this stretching occurs
it can potentially narrow
the space behind the
pectoralis minor the so-called
retro pectoralis minor
space and this is one of the
sites for impingement in
thoracic outlet syndrome.
So if impingement at the
site is actually the cause
of the patient's symptoms,
then addressing the pec
minor or using the pec
minor to correct rib 3, 4,
and 5 exhalation dysfunctions
can potentially help
not just the ribs but also
the tone of the pectoralis
minor, and in turn,
potential impingement of this
space that's involved in
thoracic outlet syndrome.
If we are performing OMT,
we should, of course,
reassess their somatic
dysfunctions after each
treatment. And in terms
of our overall clinical
management, whether it
includes OMT or not,
we should reassess the
patient's clinical response
in terms of their
symptoms, physical signs,
their function, and
quality of life.
In summary, thoracic
outlet syndrome is an
uncommon but important
diagnosis to consider
in patients with
appropriate symptoms,
especially, I
think, if they are
severe, worsen,
or become chronic.
It affects both young and
older patients, and in
the young to middle age,
in particular, asks about
vigorous or repetitive upper
body activities, especially
those involving motions
above shoulder level.
The diagnosis can be
challenging, but knowing the
various types of thoracic
outlet syndrome and performing
a careful clinical evaluation,
including incorporating
the osteopathic structural
examination, can help
you determine the cause
and aid in its management.
And given the physical
causes of thoracic outlet
syndrome, the osteopathic
manipulative approach of using
look, feel, move can and
should be incorporated into
your evaluation to enhance
your ability to diagnose
and treat modifiable factors
in the patient's care.
This concludes this lecture.
Thank you for your attention.